SAMUEL CROWELL

ightharpoonup Samuel.a.Crowell@Vanderbilt.edu in https://www.linkedin.com/in/samuel-crowell

Qualifications Summary

Ph.D. candidate with 5+ years of research experience utilizing regression analysis of large data sets to drive economic analysis. I'm looking for a fast-paced environment where I can learn and grow my career, ideally using quantitative methods to understand and solve complex problems related to financial stability and the banking system.

Experience

Vanderbilt University

Nashville, TN

 $Teaching\ Assistant$

8/2020 - 5/2024; Hours: 20

- Supervisor: Brooke Talley/Brooke.talley@Vanderbilt.edu
- Lead lectures, mentored students, and hosted weekly office hours for undergraduate level courses as a teaching assistant.
- Instructor on record for Intro Macroeconomics (Summer 2021) and the Economics of Money and Banking (Fall 2023, Spring 2024).
- Recognized in Spring 2023 when with the Rending Fels Award for Best Teaching Assistant.

Economic Research Assistant

5/2021 - Present; Hours: 20

- Supervisor: Peter L. Rousseau, Phd./Peter.L.Rousseau@Vanderbilt.edu
- Assisted Peter L. Rousseau in the research, data analysis, and writing of multiple finance and economic history projects. Utilized financial and data models to understand the development of the US's financial system.
- Utilized machine learning and regression data analysis to identify patterns in M&A activity in early 1900's industrial firms.

Bleecker Street Research

New York City, NY

Research Intern

5/2023 - 8/2023; Hours: 20

- Supervisor: Chris Drose/Chris@Bleeckerstcapital.com
- Utilized firm and industry level data to research opportunities for short biased investments.
- Uncovered anomalies in a firm's revenue reporting using Machine Learning and Regression Analysis.
- Modeled the revenue of a leading crypto exchange using high frequency transactions data.
- Gained familiarity analyzing Forms 10-k, 10-q, and other SEC public filings.

Westwood Holdings Group

Dallas, TX

Intern

6/2017 - 7/2017; Hours: 40

- Assisted in account compliance verification by identifying clients' stated investment objectives and confirming that their portfolios matched those goals.
- Gained experience documenting client interactions with the firm's CRM platform.

Education

Vanderbilt University

Nashville, TN

PhD. in Economics, 3.8 GPA

expected 8/2024

Vanderbilt University

Nashville, TN

Masters in Economics, 3.8 GPA

5/2021

Rhodes College

Memphis, TN

B.A. Economics and B.S. Mathematics, 3.9 GPA

5/2019

Areas of Expertise

- Extensive experience in data cleaning, analysis, and visualization using Excel, Python, and Stata.
- Frequently use financial and data analysis models, including OLS, VAR, Panel VAR. Comfortable using machine learning methods with large data sets.
- Extensive experience working the FDIC's Summary of Deposits Data set, and its collection of Call Reports and Uniform Bank Performance Reports. Additionally, have worked with Home Mortgage Disclosure Act and Community Reinvestment Act data sets.

Awards and Recognition

- Rending Fells Award Best Graduate Teaching Assistant (Vanderbilt University, 2023)
- Tobin Project Participant (2022)
- Graduate Tuition Award (Vanderbilt University, 2019-2024)
- Phi Beta Kappa (Rhodes College, 2019)
- Seidman Award in Economics (Rhodes College, 2019)
- Jack Russel Award in Mathematics (Rhodes College, 2017)

Volunteering and Mentorship

- Graduate Mentor, Vanderbilt Undergraduate Research Journal (2020 present)
- Council of Economic Graduate Students (2022)

Citizenship and Government Experience

- United States Citizen.
- Not a Veteran.
- No previous government work experience.

Selected Economic Research

"Local Economic Shocks and the Market for Credit"

Job Market Paper

• In this paper, I study how shocks to local labor markets are transmitted to bank balance sheets through the local deposit supply. I find that local deposit losses impact aggregate bank funding, and to compensate for these losses, banks reallocate lending to safe, liquid lending markets. In this way, an active secondary market for mortgages leads to a "flight to liquidity".

"Securities Markets and Antitrust Enforcement: Evidence from Two American Merger Movements" with Peter L. Rousseau, PhD. and Lily Gaeto Trotter, PhD.

• In this paper, we collect data on industrial stock prices from the NYSE and NY Curb markets from 1895 to 1928. We link this data to records of mergers and acquisitions and show that in the First Merger Wave, M&A activity was driven primarily by size and consolidation motives, while in the Second Merger Wave, M&A activity was driven by technology transfers and profit motives. We link these differences to changes in securities markets and antitrust enforcement.

"The Local Effect of Bank Concentration and Integration on Economic Growth" $solo\ authored$

• In this paper, I utilize panel time-series analysis to quantify the connection between county level banking markets and local economic growth. I find that in this local finance-growth nexus, local economic growth is the primary driver of bank concentration. Future extensions of this work will incorporate Double/Debiased Machine Learning to estimate panel-Vector Auto Regression models.

Professional and Academic References

- Peter L. Rousseau, PhD. (Peter.L.Rousseau@Vanderbilt.edu)
 - Dissertation Committee Member, Academic Adviser
- Sarah Quincy, PhD. (Sarah.Quincy@Vanderbilt.edu)
 - Dissertation Committee Member
- Kevin Huang, PhD. (Kevin.Huang@Vanderbilt.edu)
 - Dissertation Committee Member